Guide to the Boris Koutzen Papers, approximately 1916-2010
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
- SERIES III. Correspondence, Biographical Material And Miscellany
  - An invocation, (10 copies) (Box 51)
  - An unidentified performance (Box 51)
  - Typescript of "Journal Boris Koutzen (1944-1955)", (2 copies) (Box 53)
  - "Vassar College Orchestra / Boris Koutzen, Conductor, Presented by the Vassar College Orchestra, May 4, 1966" — Photos, news clippings, and concert programs, (Leather 3-hole binder) (Box 53)
  - Letters from Vassar personnel to Koutzen (Box 53)
  - Exhibit Materials — Concert programs, news clippings, and informative exhibit labels, 1961, 1966 (Box 53)
  - Exhibit Materials — Poster, Koutzen family attendance, Vassar and family member letters and photos, 2002 (Box 53)
  - "The works of Boris Koutzen", (printed pamphlet) (Box 53)
  - Folder from Nadia Koutzen — News clippings, concert programs, letter from Sarah Blanding to Mrs. Koutzen (Box 53)
  - Loose leaf binder regarding Koutzen's works, (fragile) (Box 50)
  - Three letters to Koutzen from Sarah Gibson Blanding, (fragile) (Box 50)
  - Frame photograph of Koutzen with Sarah Gibson Blanding, (fragile) (Box 50)
  - Obituaries, (fragile) (Box 50)
- SERIES IV. Additional Accessions from Nadia Koutzen
  - 1999 Accession
    - Vassar-related correspondence, including work contracts, 1944-1965 (Box 54)
    - A packet of information on "Bastien and Bastienne" (Box 54)
  - 2002 Accession
    - Folder of "Pappa's [sic] gift of music to Vassar" — letters, appraisals, 1960-1965 (Box 54)
    - "Broadway Rhapsody" by Bernard Kay (Manuscript, pencil) (Box 55)
    - "Broadway Serenade" by Bernard Kay (Manuscript, ink) (Box 55)
    - Black and white photo of Boris Koutzen [in front of Skinner Hall?] (Box 55)
    - "Feuille d'Album" (pencil sketch as well as ink and pencil copy) (Box 55)
    - "Legende" (Ink holograph, published edition marked for performance, and fair copy with subtitle "In the style of a Russian Folk song" (Box 55)
    - "Nocturne for violin and piano" (Pencil "copied by Inez") (Box 55)
    - Cadenza to Mozart's Violin Concerto in G Major "to my little daughter and pupil Nadia", (negative photocopy) (Box 55)
    - 2 unidentified pencil sketches (Box 55)
    - 2 unidentified pencil and ink sketches (Box 55)
    - Cadenza to Haydn Violin Concerto in C (pencil, ink and blueprint) (Box 55)
    - Kpanca (?) op. 77 1922 (pencil and ink) (Box 55)
    - Cadenza to Bockerini [sic] (3rd movement) (pencil) (Box 55)
    - Clarinet quartet score (pencil) (Box 55)
    - 1"?? odd sheet" (pencil sketch) (Box 55)
    - "Russian Siberian Folk Song" arrangement for 4 ‘cellos by Boris Koutzen (pencil) (Box 55)
    - Russian Dance from "The Tsar's Bride" (Rimsky-Korssakoff [sic]) freely adapted for four ‘cellos by Boris Koutzen (Box 55)
    - "Rondino" (Vieutemps/Koutzen) for violin and piano (ink) (Box 55)
    - "En Bateau" (Debussy) arranged for violin and piano (Box 55)
    - "Russian Dance" (Tchaikovsky/Koutzen) arranged for violin and piano (Box 55)
    - "Romance Orientale" (Rimsky-Korsakov) arranged by B. Koutzen for violin and piano with publication of Rimsky-Korsakov's "The Rose enslaves the Nightingale" ([Boston]: Boston Music Co.: 1916) (Box 55)
    - "Malaguena" Spanish Dance for violin and piano, Sarasete/Koutzen — (Ink, pencil, blueprint of violin part, negative photocopy, reduced photocopy, pencil sketches, and parts (ink) enclosed in Proof copy [?] ) (Box 55)
  - 2010 Accession
    - Koutzen's diploma from the Philadelphia Conservatory, 1940 (Box 40 (Oversize))
- Series V. 2025 Addition
  - Unprocessed materials, primarily related to Boris Koutzen and Inez Koutzen, circa 1955-2010 (Box 58)
  - Unprocessed audiocassettes, circa 1970s - circa 1990s (Boxes 59-60)
  - Unprocessed phonograph records (recordings of Koutzen's compositions/performances), circa 1950s - circa 1970s (Boxes 61-62)